Raymond Ciarrocchi
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Raymond Ciarrocchi
1953-2010
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ciarrocchi, Raymond
0.9 linear feet
The Raymond Ciarrocchi papers measure 0.9 linear feet and date from 1953-2010. Correspondence and business records document Ciarrocchi's traveling exhibition, "The Nijinsky Series," and his relationships with Tibor de Nagy Gallery and Fischbach Gallery. Also found are four sketchbooks, a thesis about American landscape painting in which Ciarrocchi figures prominently, printed material, and photographs of Ciarrocchi.
Provenance
The Raymond Ciarrocchi papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Raymond Ciarrocchi in 2011.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Landscape painter Raymond Ciarrocchi (b. 1933) has spent much of his life in New York City, exhibiting regularly and teaching at Parsons School of Design, Columbia University, and the Baruch College of City University.
A native of Chicago, he studied at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts, Washington University (B.A.), and Boston University (M.F.A.). Beginning in 1971, Tibor de Nagy Gallery presented seven solo exhibitions of Ciarrocchi's work; after 1985 he was represented by Fischbach Gallery. Typically, he works in oil on canvas, though he has produced several monotype series, including one featuring Russian ballet dancer Vaslav Nijinsky.
Scope and Content Note
The Raymond Ciarrocchi papers measure 0.9 linear feet and date from 1953-2010. Correspondence and business records document Ciarrocchi's traveling exhibition, "The Nijinsky Series," and his relationships with Tibor de Nagy Gallery and Fischbach Gallery. Also found are four sketchbooks, a thesis about American landscape painting in which Ciarrocchi figures prominently, printed material, and photographs of Ciarrocchi.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1964-2009 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Letters, 1971-2010 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings, 1980 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1971-1999 (Box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1971-2009 (Boxes 1-2, OV 3; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 6: Sketchbooks, 1953-1956 (Box 2; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, 1963-1994 (Box 2; 1 folder)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Ciarrocchi, Ray, 1933-;;;;; Fischbach Gallery; Tibor de Nagy Gallery
Subjects-Topical:
Landscape painters--New York (State)--New York; Landsape painting--United States
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Sketchbooks
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1964-2009, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  The birth certificate is a copy. Grant and award documentation concerns Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation, The Ingram Merrill Foundation, and The Pollock-Krasner Foundation, Inc.; a Macdowell Colony newsletter notes that Ciarrocchi, a recent Colony artist, was awarded a Fulbright Fellowship.
  - Birth Certificate; Registration of Marriage, 1964, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resume, circa 2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Grants and Awards, 1967-2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters, 1971-2010, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Among the personal correspondents are Karl E. Fortess, Ruth Page, and Edith Schloss. Professional letters are from galleries, colleges and schools, a few museums, the United States Department of State, and others.
  - Personal, undated, 1976-2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Professional, undated, 1971-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1981, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  A bound copy of a thesis on American landscape painting by Herbert Virgin White, in which Ciarrocchi figures prominently, is accompanied by a letter. The volume contains an inscription by the author to the artist thanking him for "inspiration, encouragement and interest."
  - White, Herbert Virgin. "American Landscape Painting: The Past Twenty Years," M.F.A. Thesis, University of Texas, San Antonio (1980), 1981, (1 vol.) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Personal Business Records, 1971-1999, Series 4:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
  This series documents consignments and gallery sales through Tibor de Nagy Gallery and Fischbach Gallery. Among the miscellaneous records are receipts for loans to museums and other institutions, and documentation of participation in exhibitions sponsored by Associated American Artists, the Art In Embassies Program, and Maine Coast Artists. Also found is detailed information about "The Nijinsky Series," a traveling exhibition of Ciarrocchi's monotypes.
  - Tibor de Nagy Gallery, 1971-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fischbach Gallery, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Nijinsky Series" Traveling Exhibition, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1973-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Printed Material, 1971-2009, Series 5:; (Boxes 1-2, OV 3; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Printed material relates almost exclusively to Ciarrocchi's exhibitions.
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, undated, 1971-1979; 1994-2009, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Posters, undated, 1985, (oversized material housed in OV 3) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Press Clippings, 1971-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Posters, undated, 1985 (Box OV 3)
- Sketchbooks, 1953-1956, Series 6:; (Box 2; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Volume 1 features landscape, still life, and figure drawings in pencil, ink, and pastel. Volumes 2-4 are devoted to pencil and ink sketches of Japanese objects, architecture, and people.
  - Volume 1: Untitled, undated, (1 vol.) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Volume 2: "Japan, 1953-1956," 1953-1956, (1 vol.) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Volume 3: Japan, undated, 1954, (1 vol.) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Volume 4: Japan, undated, 1956, (1 vol.) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 1963-1994, Series 7:; (Box 2; 1 folder)
  Photographs are of Raymond Ciarrocchi in his studio, painting outdoors, at exhibitions, with his wife and daughter, and with a group of Macdowell Colony artists.
  Views of exhibition installations at Tibor de Nagy Gallery and "The Nijinsky Series" traveling exhibition at University of Maine, Orono, are found among his personal business records (Series 4).
  - Ciarrocchi and family; with Macdowell Colony artists, undated, 1962-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)